<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Reply to the Hertford letter wherein the case of Mrs. Stout's death is more particularly considered, and Mr. Cowper vindicated from the slanderous accusation of being accessory to the same.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91666</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36282332</idno>
  <idno type="VID">150226</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240887600</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1074</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42562</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">36282332</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91666)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150226)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2236:43)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Reply to the Hertford letter wherein the case of Mrs. Stout's death is more particularly considered, and Mr. Cowper vindicated from the slanderous accusation of being accessory to the same.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for, and sold by M. Fabian ..., and J. Nutt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Stout, Sarah, d. 1699.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Cowper, Spencer, 1669-1728.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Hertford letter.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Trials (Murder) --  England.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Autopsy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150226:1"/>
            <p>A REPLY TO THE <hi>Hertford Letter:</hi> Wherein the CASE of Mrs. <hi>STOƲT</hi>'s Death Is more particularly Considered: AND Mr. <hi>COWPER</hi> Vindicated from the Slanderous Accusation of being Accessory to the Same.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for, and sold by <hi>M. Fabian,</hi> at <hi>Mercers Chapple</hi> in <hi>Cheapside;</hi> and <hi>J. Nutt,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="reply">
            <pb facs="tcp:150226:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150226:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:150226:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150226:3"/>
            <head>A Reply to the <hi>Hertford Letter,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Receiv'd your Letter from my Bookseller on the 20th of <hi>September</hi> last: And though I am far from thinking your Sentiments upon this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, were either desir'd or commanded: Yet am I well enough pleas'd with your Apology, wherein you tell us, you are very Sensible of your own Weakness, and how unfit you are to enter into a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I must confess may be of some use to the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, by forestalling their expectation of any wonderful Discovery; but for the Learned, the Compliment might have been spar'd, since the Performance does so evidently Discover what you acknowledge.</p>
            <p>The Introduction does indeed promise us great Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I shall give You my Thoughts concerning the natural Cause of Drowning, Floating of dead Bodies afterwards; the various Sentiments of the Doctors; the Manner of her Death; the Letters produced in Court; her Melancholiness; why no Mention was made of the Money; and</hi> lastly, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Two publick Experiments,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:150226:4"/>
            <p>But pray <hi>Sir,</hi> if we find your Thoughts arise from the Ebullition of a heated Fancy, and that your too ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Zeal for your Friend, has carry'd you oftentimes to over hasty Conclusions; if instead of a well grounded and rational Solution of these Phaenomena, we are only entertained with incoherent Expressions, false Grammar, Tautology, groundless Surmises, and want of Proof; in a word, if these pregnant Thoughts of your's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re found to be meer Trifles, had it not been better your Self alone had been still Master of them? Or, if there was a Necessity for their breaking out, had you not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter have communicated them only to your Friend in <hi>London,</hi> than to have expos'd your Self thus ridiculously to the Learned World?</p>
            <p>That I may make Good what I have alledg'd, I shall now proceed to your Letter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hertfort</hi> Letter, Page 3. <hi>It is a common Observation of most People not used to Dive,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Give me leave <hi>Sir</hi> here, only to question the Truth of your Proposition, Whether or no, the greater Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of those who are not Divers, have made any Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servations upon Drowning, or from their own Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can satisfy us of the Consternation that ensues plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themselves into the Water? But admit the Confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as without dispute it is) to be very Great; it may not hence follow, that the very first Moment of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mersion, Reason must be lost; or, in your own Words, that there is a Moral Impossibility to regulate their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by the Dictates of Reason.</p>
            <p>As to the laying hold of any thing in their Way, 'tis what equally happens in the Fall from a House, and seems not so much to argue a total Eclips of the Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Faculty, as a want of Time to deliberate: For the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150226:4"/> Action of falling being Instantaneous, 'tis impossible to Form a settled Act of Judgment.</p>
            <p>We all know the Prospect of sudden Death, by what way so ever, impresses a certain Horrour (which I must yet think is not so Great, to One who willfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroys Himself, as to Him who either by Accident or Constraint is put upon it); but that it leaves us imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately destitute of Choice, or a Power to refuse both, which are Acts of Free-will, and import Reason: I can't allow; as conceiving if it were so, He that willfully throws Himself from a House, and He that falls acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, would both equally lay hold of any thing, that might save their Fall.</p>
            <p>Page 4. <hi>In this Confusion,</hi> you say, <hi>it is no ways sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prising that Water, wherein they are immerced, should in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuate it self into some Vacuities, no ways adapted for its Reception.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the contrary, I must alledge that whether in or out this Confusion, it is not only very surprising, but absolutely impossible, that Water should insinuate (though ne're so cunning,) or enter into any Cavity, which is at the same time, no ways fitted, or (if you had rather) adapted to its Entrance.</p>
            <p>I will not stand to Comment on your Notion of <hi>Suction,</hi> I thought such kind of Motion had been long since exploded: For my own part, instead of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that the Lungs do suck in the Air, I think it more Rational to conceive, that as by Pulsion they are empty'd, so by the Weight of the Air from the Pressure of the Atmosphere, they are presently filled again. Be this, however, as it will, I cannot grant you that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man under Water, swallows down the same into the Gullet whilst his Senses continue: For, I doubt not but that He who designedly Drowns Himself, may choose
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150226:5"/> to let it into the Windpipe, that He may thereby the sooner be choak't.</p>
            <p>The swallowing of Air or Water down the Windpipe, is a Term I do not readily apprehend, I take Deglutition, or Swallowing, which is the sole Office of the Gullet, and Respiration, or Breathing, which only appertains to the Windpipe, to be Two different Actions, and diversly effected; whoever swallows any thing, either in or out of the Water, must, by opening the <hi>Sphincter</hi> of the <hi>Gula,</hi> let it into the Stomach: and whilst a Person under Water continues swallowing, there may be no great Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger attend him of being drowned: it being very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that during this Action, no Water gets into the Lungs; but being unable to hold out for want of Breath, he must necessarily make an Attempt to respire, when ceasing to swallow▪ the <hi>Epiglot</hi> riseth, and the Water spontaneously (if you will allow me the Expression) rusheth on the Lungs: So that when a Person is totally submerst, provided he swallows not at all, or cannot swallow longer, 'tis not only not improbable, but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve certain, that in his attempt to respire, a far greater Quantity of Water, than Air (perhaps nothing but Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) will get into the Lungs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In every Expulsion of Air out of the Lungs, the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glottis,</hi> you say, <hi>is lifted up.</hi> And is it not so, I would be informed, in every Impulsion of the Air into them?</p>
            <p>'Tis my Opinion, that this part does never exactly close upon the <hi>Larynx,</hi> but upon Deglutition: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by your Account it may be thought to be raised up like a Trap-door, and presently shut down again; I do find it a sort of Springy Body, and is, I doubt not, at all times somewhat elevated from the <hi>Glottis;</hi> unless, as I said before, at the time of swallowing: when by the Weight of the Aliments, whether liquid or solid, some
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150226:5"/> peculiar Muscles assisting, it is forced down: and after this Action is over, by its own proper Elasticity it raiseth it self again, that the successive Motions of Inspiration and Expiration, may be orderly carry'd on.</p>
            <p>When once there is any considerable Quantity of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter got into the Windpipe, I imagine this mighty Struggle of Nature doth not long continue; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot choose but wonder to hear you say, <hi>By this Struggle of Nature the Epiglot is lifted up,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It seems, in my Opinion, very natural; the Cover to the Windpipe being a springy Body, and for the most part inclining to an Horizontal Position: This, I say, consider'd, if the Mouth be full, and the Person almost spent; or though he can, yet if he will not swallow, the Nature of all Fluids is such, that they will run into any Declivity; unless (as upon another Account you have it) they are shut out, or that the Vacuity is no ways adapted to let them in.</p>
            <p>Page 5. <hi>As soon as the Senses are gone,</hi> you say, <hi>the Epiglottis is kept open by the Force of the Stream:</hi> To which I reply, that the natural Posture of the <hi>Epiglot,</hi> being such as I have described it; we might rather think the Force of the Stream should clap it down than keep it open: unless by the Force of the Stream, you mean somewhat like that of an Injection through a large <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon,</hi> whereby the said Trap-door may be beat within the <hi>Rimulae</hi> of the <hi>Larynx;</hi> but in stagnant Waters the Force of the Stream will be inconsiderable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As long as the Senses continue, they</hi> (I suppose you mean Persons under Water) <hi>swallow most of the Water which comes into their Mouths, into their Stomachs:</hi> And the rest you tell us, elsewhere, they swallow into their Windpipes. But this I deny; For as long as the Senses continue, and they can hold their Breath, they very
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150226:6"/> often swallow none: And after this, in the Case of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Drowning (which you may smile at as long as as you please) 'tis more likely by far, that they admit it into their Lungs; since by swallowing ne're so much, they do not destroy themselves; but by letting a small Quantity into the Lungs, they presently put a Period to their miserable Lives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But when they are near suffocated,</hi> you say, <hi>the Water runs into those Ducts, where it meets with the least Resistance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would, methinks, be informed what you mean by those Ducts. The Nose and Ears, I presume, are full before they are near suffocated: and if the <hi>Sphincter Gulae</hi> does oppose it Entrance into the Ventricle, what other Duct remains, unless that of the Windpipe, out of which too, after Suffocation, 'tis not impossible but it may be kept, by the Contiguity of the Tongue's Basis to the Palate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So long as Life continues,</hi> you tell us, <hi>there is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulsive struggling of Nature, to expell out of the Lungs, all those things that are noxious to them, especially Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Let me tell you, Sir, I am apt to think, this especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, will be found a great Mistake; for I doubt not, but any thing of a more uneven Texture, slipping into the Lungs, will excite much stronger Convulsions, than those from Water. But indeed, according to some Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments I lately made, I could not perceive the Marks of those violent Convulsions you here speak of.</p>
            <p>I took a Dog, and by a Weight directly sunk him under Three Foot of Water, which was so clear, that I could perceive what happen'd to him; and to be plain with you, I observed, that for almost a Minute, he threw his Head disorderly about, before he gap't; upon which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150226:6"/> the Water getting into his Windpipe in half a Minute more, he fell down with his Neck to the Bottom, void of Sense and Motion.</p>
            <p>After this, I plung'd another, somewhat less; when, in like manner as the former, I found when he had turned his Neck two or three times about, he was to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance dead in a Minute's time.</p>
            <p>Now in all this, there were none of those Violent Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, to throw the Water out of the Lungs, discernable; or did I think it at all rational, to expect the same forced into the Cavity of the <hi>Thorax;</hi> either by dilating the Pores of the thin Membrane that invests the Lungs, as Quick-silver is forced by the Pressure of a Hand through a Piece of Leather; or by a Rupture of their Tunicle, or by some minute Vessels not yet described by Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists. And the Reason of my thinking so is this, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I could perceive little more to effect it, but the specifick Gravity of the Water; which, according to the Laws of the Libration of Liquors, I take to be inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable.</p>
            <p>I know of no Physician that boasts of a <hi>Ne plus ultra</hi> in Anatomy: nor should I expect any such Pretension from a Physician, so soon as from the Anatomist. These Two, you know, are not always ins<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>parable Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But as to your Instance about the <hi>Empyema;</hi> tho' I think it foolish to deny Facts, when I am unable to account for the Manner how they are brought about: Yet I see nothing to hinder me from believing, that very often, where the Matter you speak of is cast forth by Excreation; the Lungs have suffer'd a Solution of their Continuity. In Two Persons I have inspected, who died under these Circumstances, it was apparent; in both of which, as I suppose, from a preceding <hi>Peripneu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> there had been <hi>Abscesces</hi> formed in the <hi>Lobes</hi> of the <hi>Lungs,</hi> which had rotted their outward <hi>Membrane;</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:150226:7"/> so that whether the Purulent Matter, which was cough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, came from the said <hi>Abscess,</hi> or whether some of that which fluctuated on the <hi>Diaphragm,</hi> might not also be imbibed by the ulcerated Lung, was very uncertain.</p>
            <p>The Injection of bitter Liquors affecting the Throat, if they are cast into a <hi>Fistula</hi> which took its Rise from an Internal Apostem: or otherwise, if the Penetration has been of long continuance, and discharged great Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of faetid, Ichorous or Corrosive Matter: I should less wonder the Experiment should answer; for in these Cases the Tone of the <hi>Viscera</hi> is very much weakened, the Patient very frequently dyes tabid, and we find up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Dissection, that very commonly the Lungs are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted. It may happen also in a <hi>Recent Puncture;</hi> but then we may be likewise sometimes uncertain, whether the Membrane of the Lungs received no Damage.</p>
            <p>I desire not that greater Stress should be laid upon these Cases, than they will readily bear: but this I must aver, that in Penetrations of the Chest, it does not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways happen: For in a <hi>Puncture</hi> I have seen injected, and a <hi>Fistula</hi> of this part, into which I have cast at times, several Ounces of a bitter Decoction, with a Tincture of <hi>Myrh</hi> and <hi>Aloes:</hi> during which, I can safely say, I never heard any such Complaint, though I have purposely inquired.</p>
            <p>Your Citation of Mr. <hi>Boyl</hi>'s Citation from <hi>Wallaeus,</hi> if Matter of Fact, might be Preter-natural: And as to his finding the same divers times, how diligent soever he might be, rather than shew my self uncivil to him, by saying 'tis false, I shall turn <hi>Sceptick,</hi> and suspend my Assent till I am better satisfied: At present I cannot see, if there was an admission of Air, through Pores much smaller than those made by the longer sort of Peas, into the Cavity of the Chest, how Respiration could be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150226:7"/> on: and I must needs think, that Dr. <hi>Garth</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark upon the Tryal<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cowper</hi>'s Tryal, p. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> is very pertinent: where he tells us, <hi>There is a great Providence in such a Texture; for if</hi> (saith he) <hi>there were any large Pores in this Membrane, the Air would pass through into the Cavity of the</hi> Thorax, <hi>and prevent the Dilatation of the</hi> Lungs, <hi>and consequently there would be an end of Breathing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that I might put this Matter yet farther out of Controversy, being willing to be made sensible of the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most Efforts of a Drowning Creature, and the Result of the most violent Struglings it could make to save it self; I sent for a Dog, and lest you should find fault had I made use of a Tub, I procur'd the use of a Distiller's <hi>Back,</hi> which, if I may call it so, is a sort of Trough, containing in Dimention Thirty Foot of Length, and half so much of Breadth. Into this, when fill'd with Water, I caus'd the Animal to be cast, having before order'd his Four Feet to be ty'd together.</p>
            <p>By the Force of the Fall he was plunged over Head and Ears, but rising up again, made to the side as well as he could, and though several times repulsed, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued strugling, and by the Liberty of his Hind-feet, often raised his Head above the Water; upon which, seeing no likelihood of his being drowned under a very long time, I ordered him to be taken out, and his Hind-feet also to be fastened together. Thus he was a second time thrown in, and continued strugling sometimes under, and sometimes above Water with his Head and Neck, in a quarter of an Hour's time his Navel started, and soon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there was a visible <hi>Prolaps</hi> of the <hi>Intestinum Rectum:</hi> Having thus between while had the Liberty of an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Respiration, it was half an Hour before he had done strugling; after which, under Water he gaped several times. When dead I left him, and returned Five Hours after; at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150226:8"/> which time I desired he might be taken out with his Head erected, that we might lose no Water.</p>
            <p>I think, if it had been possible, I had Reason in this Case to expect Water in the Two Cavities, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Thorax</hi> and the <hi>Abdomen,</hi> which seemed much tumefied, but was so far from it, that upon the opening the <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonaeum,</hi> instead of an Inundation, I found not a Drop of Water; and even the small <hi>Intestines</hi> had received very little, if any at all from the <hi>Pilorus.</hi> What was contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Stomach was much short of half a Pint, or little more than Four or Five Ounces. Having raised the <hi>Sternon,</hi> we perceived the <hi>Thorax,</hi> in like manner as the <hi>Abdomen,</hi> perfectly clear of Water. Out of the <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe</hi> there issued a Spumous Matter, and the whole of what we pressed from its <hi>Ramifications,</hi> was about Three Ounces.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, have I given you a faithful History of the Fact; but if you think the Experiment was made clandestinely, or that the Dog was half strangled before thrown into the Water, as you pitifully insinuate about Mr. <hi>Cowper</hi>'s Experiments; for your farther Satisfaction, you may be informed of Mr. <hi>Harrison,</hi> without <hi>Bishopsgate;</hi> of <hi>Tho. Serjeant,</hi> Esq; Gentleman Porter to the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London;</hi> Mr. <hi>John Lichfield, Surgeon,</hi> with sundry other Persons, as Honest as Judicious. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
            <p>Page 6. <hi>Water is as frequently found in the Cavity of the</hi> Abdomen, <hi>as the</hi> Thorax.</p>
            <p>It may be so; but if the <hi>Stomach, Guts, &amp;c.</hi> in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and the <hi>Lungs</hi> in the latter, continue firm and sound (as it is reported they were in Mrs. <hi>Stout</hi>) I cannot see how it should happen to be found in either. I must confess, I have never seen it, nor was there any thing like it in my late Experiment. If the <hi>Viscera</hi> are putrid
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150226:8"/> I should not wonder at it; but if otherwise, I should be thankful to your Microscoptick Anatomist to shew me how or which way it should enter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As soon as the</hi> Lungs, Stomach, &amp;c. <hi>are full of Water, the Body naturally sinks,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I suppose the <hi>&amp;c.</hi> includes the <hi>Thorax</hi> and <hi>Abdomen,</hi> as well as the <hi>Guts;</hi> but though the <hi>Lungs▪ Stomach,</hi> and the <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are full of Water, in the Sense of Fulness here meant: I deny that the Body will always sink; as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving seen the contrary, and can bring Proof of the same.</p>
            <p>Page 7. <hi>It is observable,</hi> you say, <hi>that Human Bodies after Death, admit no Water; because as soon as Death seises a Man, the Sphincter Muscles in all Parts do natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally contract themselves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How it is in Human Bodies I can't say, having made no Experiment of that kind: But that it is always so in other Animals I deny, and indeed can see no Reason why it should not be admitted for a Paralel Case. For though you say, the Sphincter Muscles do contract themselves, yet the Epiglot stands open; so that unless the Tongue and Palate by their Contiguity, or some Spumous Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter already in the Windpipe, intercept its passage: What hinders, in a supine Position of the Body, but that some small quantity of Water may slip within the Rimulae? But whether or not the Sphincters do always naturally contract themselves before Death, may be disputed: For they sometimes labour at that time with such a Paralysis, as occasions a Resolution of their Nervous Fibres, and forces them involuntarily to let go their Contents: Thus nothing is more common than for dying Animals, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rational or Irrational (if soon before they did not Exonerate) to let fall their Urine and Intestinal Fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:150226:9"/>
            <p>That I might inform my self whether the Water would get into a Dead Body, I caused a Dog to be suffocated over the Fumes of a Spirituous Liquor, prepar'd for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stillation, in the time of its Fermentation; and though his Nose was held some little distance from the Surface, yet it stiffled him to Death in two or three Minutes time, after this he was thrown into the Water, and sunk pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently to the bottom, where he lay several Hours. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carefully taken out, I open'd his Throat, and found the Epiglot (as is always usual) raised from the Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe, which inclining downwards, there was discharged about three Spoonfulls of fair Water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 7. The immediate floating of Human Bodies, thrown dead into the Water, I believe to be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain: And whoever goes about to establish it for an infallible Hypothesis, I must needs think very rash if not guilty of a downright folly. For, though your Sea-men should tell me a Thousand idle Stories, I know there are so many causes that may alter the Case, that it would be very rediculous to credit so bold an Assertion. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not say, I have as yet try'd the Experiment on a Humane Body, but of those other Animals (both alive and dead when thrown into the Water) which I have made use of, there was but one which floated, and that I thought most likely to be found at the bottom; as having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved most Water into the Lungs and Stomack. If the Dead Body of an Ascitical Person should not sink, it might seem strange. Oon the other hand, if that of a pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tympanitical, should not Float, it would be equally a wonder.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If the Person dy'd in the very Act of Inspiration, the Lungs</hi> you say, <hi>will be full of Air,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Here <hi>Sir,</hi> you must give me leave to think you very much out of the way, for unless in the case of some ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150226:9"/> sudden and violent Death, I am apt to believe all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons finish their Life in the Act of Expiration; and even in the most sudden setting aside that of strangling by a Ligature, where the Air is forcibly included, and its passage from the Windpipe intercepted; I make it a <hi>Question</hi> whether the last Motion of the Lungs, is not that of its Systole or Contraction. For, although to outward appearance, a Man or other Creature may be thought to die inspiring, and seem perfectly devoy'd of Sence and Motion: Yet by laying any polisht or <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonous</hi> body to the Mouth and Nostrils, there is often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a Damp contracted on the same, which is nothing but the Air insensibly proceeding out of the Lungs, and condensed on the surface of the said Body.</p>
            <p>'Tis this general Opinion, that hath given Rise to that very common Expression, when we would signify the Death of a Friend, by saying he is expired, or hath breathed out his last. But admit the Assertion good, of Dying in the Act of Inspiration, it will not follow that any Dying Person can take a tenth Part of the Air, he did in perfect Health: And so consequently cannot fill his Lungs with Air. For not to instance in <hi>Asthmatic</hi> Persons, who at all times take but little Air, by reason of the Obstructions of the <hi>Bronchia;</hi> and are therefore forced upon quick breathing: It is very rational to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that immediately before Death, the constrictive Fibres are much weakned, the Blood begins to Stagnize in all Parts, and being carried by the <hi>Arteria venosa</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lungs, faster than thrown off by the <hi>vena Arteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osa,</hi> into the left <hi>Ventricle</hi> of the Heart; a great part of the <hi>Pulmonary Cells</hi> are so stuffed, that they can ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit but little Air: So that the quantity of what we take in perfect Health, and that which we receive Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is vastly disproportionate.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:150226:10"/>
            <p>By filling the <hi>Thorax</hi> with the same Air forced into the Windpipe, unless you mean filling the Lungs in the <hi>Thorax,</hi> it seems of kin to the <hi>Jargon</hi> of filling the <hi>Thorax,</hi> with Water out of the Lungs. For my Part, I have several times through a <hi>Tube,</hi> blow'd with as great Force as I could into the <hi>Lobes</hi> of the Lungs, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing at the same time, a lighted Candle to be held nigh their Extremities, and round about them; I never could perceive the least Motion of the Flame, whereby I might conjecture the Air had any vent: So that I must think it impossible that either Air or Water, whilst their <hi>Texture</hi> continues Firm, can insinuate it self into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of the <hi>Thorax;</hi> till you can bring me some of the diligent <hi>Wallaeus</hi>'s Gentlemen, that have Pores in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vesting Membrane of their Lungs, as big as the longer sort of Peas.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 9. I think it very likely, that a dead Body will be more Buoyant in Salt than in Fresh-water. But your Experiment I take to be inconclusive, for unless you had said that a Ship will sink some Inches lower in a Sea of Fresh-water, than in one of Salt: Your Adversary may object, that the reason of the lower sinking in the <hi>Thames,</hi> may perhaps be as much owing to the want of Depth, as Salt.</p>
            <p>The Discordance of the Physicians, is best perceiv'd by reading over the Tryal, some part of the Disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as I remember, did consist in this: That whereas on the King's Part, it was affirm'd the Lungs of Mrs. <hi>Stout,</hi> were firm and sound, and not the least ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Water in the <hi>Thorax;</hi> for the Prisoner Mr. <hi>Cowper,</hi> it was reply'd, that if the investing Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane of the Lungs was sound, it was rediculous to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Water in the Chest their Enclosure.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:150226:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> For the King, it was thought impossible that any Person thrown alive into the Water, should be drowned without swallowing or taking in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the same, into the Stomach and other Cavities; Whereas for the Prisoner it was thought very Possible two or three Ounces might be sufficient to Drown any Submersed Person. And this leads me to your <hi>Tenth Page,</hi> where I find you much concern'd, that Mr. <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi>'s Physicians should strenuously urge, that so small a quantity of Water was sufficient for this Purpose: Which you say they grounded on a Private Experiment on a Dog half-hang'd, you being apt to think that there was Artifice in the Case: and indeed so should I, if I were sure they had half hang'd him; but if you were told so in your sleep it may happen to be false; or if not, I think you are but little obliged to any Person, who who was so officious as to tell you an untruth. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, that you may not be told of any Artifice made use of in my Experiments, I shall refer you to the foresaid Mr. <hi>Serjeant.</hi> He is a Gentleman very curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in these Enquiries, a Man of unquestionable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity, and very well known in our City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his presence, with divers others, I caused a Dog who had been kept fasting almost twenty four Hours, to be plunged under Water, without suffering him to rise: When he had been dead some time, I took him with his Head erected, that we might not lose a drop of Water he had taken in. Having made a Ligature on the Gula, I turned down the Larynx, and with a moderate Pressure, there was discharged of Water mixed with a Spume or Froth, about four large Spoonfuls.</p>
            <p>After this, I came to the Stomach, which I percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be very lank and flaccid, when cutting into
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150226:11"/> it, there was not a Drop of Water to be found; nor indeed the least remains of the Chylous Juice, which had been before carry'd off through his long Fasting, so that the wrinkles of the inward Membrane were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conspicuous.</p>
            <p>Soon after I drowned another before the same Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and do assure you have all imaginable reason to perswade my self, that all the Water he had received was let into the Lungs, which did not exceed two Ounces and an half: But in this latter, (having, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to us, been fed a little before) the Stomach was half full of indigested Aliments, yet no appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Water, which in Drowning we could sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he had gulped down.</p>
            <p>I come now to your Pleasantry with Dr. <hi>Sloan,</hi> who it seems was so unhappy as to tell the Judge, that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of that kind were very uncommon; and least some Ignorant Person should be to seek for the meaning of the words, here is a Parenthesis clapt in, to tell us, that by Cases of this kind is meant <hi>(for Mrs.</hi> Stout <hi>to be Drowned without any Water in her.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I thank you Sir for your Information, till now I did not think the Doctors Words were so Mysterious, but harmlesly gave them a quite different Constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which before you were pleased to be so witty with them, I thought very natural; and having since asked others, they tell me the Dr. means the Cases of Drowned Bodies Remarkt upon, especially when they have been laid six Weeks under Ground, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards inspected to find Water. Now, Sir, if since the Creation of Man or Woman either, you have heard of such a Case before, or if in the Multiplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of your Practice, you have met with any thing like it, I think 'tis great Injustice that you have so long conceal'd it.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150226:11"/>
            <p>I would gladly know precisely what you mean by Drowning. You think that no Person can properly be said to be Drown'd, who hath not swallow'd, (I should rather like received or let in, because swallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as I have already told you, is proper to the Gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let) above two or three Ounces of Water; and I think, that if under Water those two or three Ounces do effect his Destruction, he is as truly said to be Drowned, as if he had taken in two or three Gallons.</p>
            <p>If Respiration could by any Contrivance, be secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a Person under Water, he would be then in no danger of Drowning. Again, set him up to the Chin, and if it were possible, let him swallow a Tun; tho' it may be otherways mischievous, it will not drown him. For if, as may be inferred from your Opinion, Drowning must be measured by a great Quantity of Liquor swallow'd into the Stomach, we have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of those Drowned Persons, some of them top full, daily reeling about our Streets in <hi>London,</hi> and I believe you have some few of them in your Town of <hi>Hertford:</hi> Hitherto we have called them Drunken Persons; and you will find it a very difficult matter to perswade them, that they are properly or truly Drowned.</p>
            <p>Since then it is not the greater quantity swallowed into the Stomach, but the lesser taken into the Lungs, that kills the Creature, and since there is no such thing at all as Drowning, but by that smaller Quantity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring the said part; I reckon that if a Man dies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Water, without the distinction of more or less Water taken in, he is as much and as really Drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as any thing can be. I know the word is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ambiguous, and Custom has apply'd it different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for if a Person upon Land, by Liquor acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150226:12"/> rushing on the Lungs, or as it is call'd, going the wrong way, receives his Death: This I say is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Suffocation; but if the same thing betides him under Water, we usually call it Drowning; tho' the latter is as much Suffocated as the former. But I have already been too long on this matter, and shall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 11. I hope by this time, you are no great stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the meaning of that general Question you take notice of, about Water in the Thorax; if being sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of the Blunder, they had ingeniously quitted it; I believe it had been much better; but whether or no their persisting in it has been any advantage to them, the Learned World must judge.</p>
            <p>I cannot think the investing Membrane of the Lungs, so easily torn in Coughing: if it should there may an Ulcer of the Lungs ensue, for the Solution would not presently, if at all, be re-united: But what of this, or what would you infer. I cann't perswade my self there is any Coughing under Water, that should break their Continuity.</p>
            <p>I find the Dr. is not yet got out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your Clutches. He brings us, poor Gentleman, so many <hi>if's</hi> and <hi>and's;</hi> that his Sentences happen to prove un-intelligible; for where he tells us, that if there was a great Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a great deal of the Water would rise up in Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours and Steams, and go off that way; we are at a Loss it seemeth what way he means.</p>
            <p>Page 12. <hi>I can't imagine,</hi> say you, <hi>by that way, what way he means.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know not what you may imagine, yet I cannot think you altogether so dull as you pretend: But others do imagine, that by the way of Steams and Vapours, he means the way of Steams and Vapours:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150226:12"/> or if 'twill be more easy to your imagination, under the form, after the manner, or by the way of Evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Through what passages these Vapours were to make their way, was another Question, which if you were to ask him, he would perhaps tell you thro' the Pores of the Body. But it seems, to serve a turn, all Out-lets must be barr'd and bolted; the Sphincters must be lockt up, and all the coverings of the Body grow so dense and compact, that not one poor Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puscle shall gain its Liberty: so that altho' some steams cannot extricate themselves from putrid Flesh, yet others will get through Plaister'd and Brick-Walls, nay the very stones themselves are not a Fence against their Penetration. But if a certain Person, present at the Dissection, does not retract, I was told there was a moisture somewhat like these Steams, on the Burial Cloaths of Mrs. <hi>Stout;</hi> in others I have been informed it has been frequently observed: But rather than this Putrefactive Moisture, or sort of Dew, which has been seen upon the Shrowds of the Dead, should be thought to arise from the Body: I suppose you would choose to account for it, from the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean Damps, working through the Coffin, and so setling on the Corps.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 13. I make no question, but that dead Flesh, whether in or out of Water, will quickly grow pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid: but which of them will be so soonest, I can't be positive, tho' I am rather inclining to Dr. <hi>Garth</hi>'s Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and to think that Water will rather retard than hasten putrefaction: In a little time I shall be better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to give Satisfaction to them who require it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 14. You must excuse me, if I don't come up to your Belief, that there was a <hi>Lapsús Linguoe,</hi> in the Dr's. Distinction of Accident and Design, as believing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150226:13"/> it founded both on Reason and Experience: but if you will allow them as much Difference as may be found in your witty Simile, <hi>P.</hi> 16. between the Person who putteth the Halter about his own Neck, and one (as you express it) that the Hang-man forceth it on. I know not whether they will desire any more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 17. The Animals I drown'd, had all of them much Froth came from their Mouths and Nostrils; and after having taken out of one of them, the Lungs and Wind-pipe, and laid them on a Table, I obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this Spumous Matter plentifully to rise up, and to run over the <hi>Epiglottis:</hi> insomuch that it seemed like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Lobes</hi> might be quickly emptied of their Water by this way of Purgation. I cannot say this Froth is peculiar to Drown'd Persons; for tho' perhaps the Lungs may not furnish the Matter, yet to Persons dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherways, there very often happens so quick a Ferment in the Stomach, that the Contents thereof are frequently Discharged by the Gullet, under this Appearance. I know 'tis positively asserted by one of the Physicians, that if Mrs. <hi>Stout</hi> had not been Drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there had been none of this Purgation, I suppose he means from the Wind-pipe, and then I am encli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the same Opinion.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Herriot</hi> must be answerable for his own Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, I am so far from defending him, that if he or any one else, should tell me it was so general a Rule, as did admit of no Exception, I should give lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle heed to them, since I find it very uncertain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 19. Having now, as you suppose cleared the way, and knockt down all before you: the next thing is your Account of her Death: but if I am not much deceiv'd, the Entrance to it, is either thro' your unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for the Task, or the weakness of your Intellect, usher'd in with a very great mistake.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150226:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>If this Gentlewoman,</hi> say you, <hi>was not Drowned, as the Doctors and Surgeons for the Prisoners, seem to insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How! Did the Doctors for the Prisoners insinuate that She was not Drowned, I profess I thought they had all taken it for granted that She was Drowned. Dr. <hi>Crell,</hi> I think in particular was a Physician for the Prisoners, and He expresly tells the Judge<note n="*" place="margin">Cowpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Tryal, p.</hi> 3</note> that He is not to des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant upon the Matter of Fact, whether She Drowned her self: Yet saith He, my firm Opinion is that She was Drowned.</p>
            <p>Now if to be positive or firmly to believe She was Drowned, be the same thing as insinuating she was not Drowned: I see not how any Man can rightly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend anothers meaning, but by the Rule of Contraries. I confess you have already told us of the weakness of your Intellect, but how weak soever that may be, I must needs think your Memory is very Treacherous. Now as to the Manner of Mrs. <hi>Stout</hi>'s Death.</p>
            <p>First then we are to understand, <hi>She was knocked down with a Blow upon Her left Ear.</hi> Secondly, <hi>After She was down, She was throtled with the Gripe of a strong Hand. And</hi> Thirdly, <hi>That the Person who throtled Her, might gripe the Stronger, He rested his Arm upon Her Breast.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On my word <hi>Sir</hi> you have made it out extreamly well, I find 'tis a rare thing to have a quick Invention: And I must tell you for your Incouragement, 'tis a Question whether the best Mathematitian in our City of <hi>London,</hi> could have done it more exactly. 'Twas well your fruitful Genious was consulted to unty this Knot, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise we might have met with much difficulty, and perhaps had never been able to have solved so many perplexing Phaenomena with so much perspicuity.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150226:14"/>
            <p>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>st con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>as very unlucky for Mr. <hi>Cowper,</hi> these setlings hapned so pat for your Learned Comments: But had they been elsewhere, I fear they would not have escaped your penetrating Judgment. Thus upon the Belly they might have been made by kneeling to keep Her down: Upon her Back by falling on the said Part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Ground Her Thighs might happen to be trampled on in the Scuffle, and nothing more likely, than that some Body should lye upon her Legs, for fear she should rise again before they had dispatch'd her. Thus, right or wrong, rather than it should be thought she was accessory to her own Death, we must find out the best means we can, on which to ground a Perswasion that it happened otherwise, and that of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity there must be violence in the Case.</p>
            <p>We come now to the Reasons, why you can't believe she did destroy her self: which I shall briefly speak to, as they lye in order; and, with you, submit my self to better Judgments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The first is, Because she was found without her Gown and Nigthtrail, which</hi> (that we may have a Salve for every Soar) <hi>were very probably torn in the Scuffle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to this, I must think it rational to suppose, that she her self might take them off, to promote (as she might imagine) the speedy sinking, or prevent the Discovery of her Body, by their spreading on the Surface of the Water; nor do I see any great Difficulty in the Thought, that a <hi>Norwich</hi> Stuff may be rotted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Water, in as little time as the Gown was, of which we are speaking. If the Nightrail be never found, I hope it does not follow that she was Murder'd: I should rather think, if the Gown was brought and thrown in afterwards, so might the Nightrail too; which would have been as easily rotted elsewhere, as the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150226:14"/> Gown, and with the same Trouble both might have been cast into the Water. I can't suppose, admitting it had been in the River from the time of her Drowning, that it would have been always in one Place; but rather carry'd by the Stream under Water, sometimes to one place sometimes to another; sometimes lodg'd and sometimes at Liberty, as we find other Trumpery will be under a Current: So that supposing the Miller had very diligently clear'd that very Stake, but half an hour before; what hinders the possibility but that the next half hour, the Gown either by it self, or together with other Trash, might be carry'd thither by the Stream and lodg'd?</p>
            <p>Page 20. Secondly, <hi>Because she was found Floating, of which you make no doubt, because it was Sworn by se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Witnesses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have already taken Notice, that from this, there can be nothing certainly infer'd; Dead Bodies thrown into Water, I am satisfi'd will often Sink, and Drowned Bodies sometimes will not: But as to the Case before us, 'tis plain that some of those who view'd the Body, gave a different Relation from some others. Thus some of them said She did Float though it was under Water, whilst others, who should know best, being the Parish Officers and employ'd by the Coroner to take Her out, Depose, that the Body lay half a Foot under Water, and that for any thing they could perceive, Her Feet might touch the bottom, and farther that when She was hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved up, there were several Sticks and Flags on which She rested; but without all this, <hi>Sir,</hi> I think it very Natural for a Dead Body which is always Buoyant, in a Current four or five Foot deep, by the bare Force of the Stream when it meets with a sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nting Opposition, to be raised from the bottom.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150226:15"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Because Her Belly was not at all Swollen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was it at all necessary, though Drowned, that it should.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Because no Water came out of Her, when lifted out of the Water, nor purged from Her after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, with Submission, is a mistake: For, though there is no quantity of Water taken Notice of, to issue from Her; yet is it agreed on both Sides, that She did purge at the Mouth and Nostrils: Some say more, others less. The two Principal who took Her out, and stood by for some time afterwards, do affirm that the Froth came out after such a Manner, as to run down the sides of the Face, and that as it was wiped of, fresh Froth came presently on again; which Doctor <hi>Crell</hi> does assert, could not have hapned had She been strangled or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways kill'd before. Whether this be so or not, I believe it very Possible, where little Water is received (and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little will suffice to Drown a Person), if there be so great a Purgation at the Mouth and Nostrils, most if not all the Water, may be turned into a Spumous Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, at least so much that there will be no absolute Neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity, for Water to run out upon the Motion of the Body afterwards.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Because Her Inwards were not putrified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After six Weeks time, I should indeed have expected Putrifaction from any Person under Ground, that had not been Imbalmed, without regard to Water taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Body; which whether or no it hasten Putrifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, is very disputable: What it may do under the Earth I know not, but I much question whether Dead-flesh, cover'd over with Water, will grow Putrid so soon as that which is expos'd to the immediate Contact of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150226:15"/> Air. Of this I shall be able to say more in a little time and for the present leave it as a Problem undecided.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>From the several distinct setlings of Blood, unusual in Drowned Persons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the Tryal, it is affirm'd by Mr. <hi>Camlin,</hi> that both Mr. <hi>Dimsdale</hi> and Himself having viewed the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, did give it in as their Opinion to the Coroner, that there were no other settlements or stagnations of the Blood than that what may usually happen to Drowned Bodies. Mr. <hi>Camlin</hi> instances in the Child for one, but whether that were so or not, I have perceived it my self on the Superfice of a Drowned Body, nor do I see why it may not be found on the Neck and Breast, as soon as on other Parts.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>From the continual Disturbance, Mrs</hi> Gurrey <hi>was under, both in Mind and Body, nevertheless She would not discover it, till She was almost frightned out of Her Senses, by the Voice, as She thought, of Mrs.</hi> Stout, <hi>which utter'd these Words, Divulge, Conceal nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Mrs. <hi>Gurrey</hi> was disturbed in Mind, it would seem strange that she should not be disturbed in Body; the latter being, as I suppose, seldom or never easy, whilst the former is under Trouble or Disquiet. But whether Mrs. <hi>Gurrey's</hi> mighty Disturbance, had other Rise than a Whim of the Brain, founded upon a strong Preposses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Fancy, may very reasonably be question'd: For my part, I look on it so natural, for a doating ignorant old Woman to be terrified with the Disorder of her own Imagination, before hand perverted by too deep R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; though the same has nothing but a Chimaera to support it, that I am never startled when I hear of their Pretences to Voices and Revelations. These you know are not ingrossed, though more peculiar to a distinct Sect. So that if once such Persons happen to be strongly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150226:16"/> opinion'd that any thing may be so, they need but fall asleep for a Confirmation that it is so.</p>
            <p>Had you not already acquainted us with the Weakness of your Intellect, and your Incapacity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I should have been startled that a Man of Learning and Solid Judgment should build on the idle Fancies of a dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing old Woman. I think, how greatly soever she might be disturbed before in Mind or Body, she has now more Reason to be concern'd, that by her fond belief of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, those Men should be brought into danger of their Lives, whom we have a great deal of Reason to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve were as Innocent as her self, and little or none to to think they should be guilty of such a horrid Fact as they were accus'd of.</p>
            <p>Page 21. <hi>Eighthly, from what is sworn by the</hi> Gurreys <hi>against their Lodgers at the Tryal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Could I believe all to be true that the <hi>Gurreys</hi> swore, I should make no question of the Likelyhood of these Mens Guilt: But that they did stretch in some things, is very easy to believe, by some Particulars at the Tryal, and by their Behaviour before, at, and after the same, we have great Inducements to persuade us that they did so in others. Thus it is proved that <hi>Gurrey</hi> himself went out of the Court in a boasting way, to tell some of his Acquaintance, <hi>That he had done</hi> Cowper<hi>'s Business;</hi> or to that effect. And at another time he said, <hi>That if Mr.</hi> Cowper <hi>had visited Old Mrs.</hi> Stout, <hi>none of this Trouble had befaln him.</hi> Another thing discovers the Malice of the Prosecution, in that though themselves suspected Mrs. <hi>Stout</hi>'s Maid, yet this was not to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, for fear of taking off her Evidence: And if his Wife could so readily turn the Fifty Shillings, Mr. <hi>Marson</hi> had that Day received in <hi>Southwark,</hi> for Business done in the <hi>Borough-Court,</hi> into Fifty Pound,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150226:16"/> supposed to be paid him for Murthering Mrs. <hi>Sarah Stout</hi> at <hi>Hertford;</hi> she might by the same kind of Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or by a Mistake, understand all the rest.</p>
            <p>It seems indeed to me, the most notorious Absurdity can be imagin'd, that had these Men really came down on such a Design, they should go directly to tell their Landlady, Mrs. <hi>Stout's</hi> Business was done, they had spoiled her Courting Days, and that one of them had received Fifty Pounds for doing her Business.</p>
            <p>In Matters of this Nature, where we can have nothing but idle Stories, and an Old Wive's Dream to raise the Suspicion; I think it highly behoves us, before we pass our Censure, to pay a just Regard to the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter and Reputation of the Person. Thus indeed, tho' it will be impossible for Mr. <hi>Cowper</hi> to clear himself, in the Opinion of every one who knows nothing of him: Yet I am ready to think there are few who know him (unless some particular Persons, that upon any Terms, would willingly ruine the Interest of his Family in that County) will be brought to a Perswasion he could so barbarously imbrue his Hands in Blood, though instead of the pretended One Thousand Pound, he might have gained Ten: And as to the other Persons, 'tis visible they live in Credit and Reput<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion, their Characters well at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested, and not one of them in the least likely, to make an Assassine, for the Lucre of Five Hundred Pounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly, From the Sentiments of the Grand Jury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I must needs think that on so formal an Indictment drawn up against these Gentlemen; such strenuous Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of their being Guilty; so foul a Crime charged on them; such a Circumstance attending, as that of Mr. <hi>Cowper</hi>'s being last in her Company, and the others of his Acquaintance: especially when Mrs. <hi>Gurrey</hi>'s Tale had been set out with abundance of Aggravation; I see,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150226:17"/> I see not how for Publick Satisfaction as well as Private the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and Jury could do less than Find the Bill. But as to the Perty Jury as you call them, I wish you had nam'd those several, who did believe her murder'd after the Tryal. I am assur'd that some of them have openly declar'd, they thought the Gentlemen we speak of, had been so much abus'd, that the Prosecutor's Estate, if it were ten times larger than it is, was little enough to make them Reparation.</p>
            <p>As to the Letters produc'd in Court, your Thoughts it seems are, <hi>That they are not of a Legitimate, but a Spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Issue:</hi> And why?</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Because the Stile doth no ways suit her Character.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Author of the <hi>Hertford-Letter</hi> had no extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, or perhaps no Knowledge at all of her, but takes every thing on Trust from her Friends and Relations: he ought not to be so positive, that the Stile does no way suit her Character. If by Stile, as the Word gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally is understood, you mean the Order of her Thoughts, or the Manner of her Expression, you must own she might have Sense enough to be the Author of those Compositions. But I find you make so bold with the Use of Words, and take them so differently from other Learned Men, that in some places it Occasions a little Difficulty to understand you. If by Stile then, as I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, you wou'd signify the Subject of the Discourse, or the Matter of the Composure; I have more Reason to think, than I will at present make Publick, that these Letters do well enough suit her Character, with some that knew her. And I must tell you, that I am ready to believe, had her Mother been asked the Question some Months before she dyed, when she had some Words with her one Evening in the Garden; or about the time when <hi>Theophilus</hi> was sent for to reprove her, about her
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150226:17"/> falling from the Light: I say at these times, I can't think her Mother would have deny'd, but that these Letters might have been suitable to her Character. However, she is now out of a Capacity to defend her self, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Account it might seem ill, with Contempt to tread upon her Ashes; I shall therefore say no more, but that I would not have you too busy with the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, lest you should happen to make good an old Proverb.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Because the Mother doth affirm, the Letter shewn in Court, was of a smaller Character, than ever she observed her Daughter to write, neither doth her Brother think them to be Genuine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would it not have been very odd, if the Mother and Brother, who came to secure the Reputation of so near a Relation (though never so well satisfied that it was her Hand) should have said otherwise than they did. For my part, I take both their Answers to be so unsatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, not to say foolish, that nothing but the Relation they were speaking for, can plead their Excuse.</p>
            <p>The Mother being asked by the Judge, whether she thought it was her Daughters Hand, reply's only, <hi>how should I know? I know she was no such Person, her Hand may be counterfeited.</hi> Being question'd again what she would say to it, if it had been written in a more Sober Stile, She answers, <hi>I shan't say it to be her Hand, unless I had seen her write it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Brother being interrogated on the same Question, says, <hi>'Tis like his Sisters Hand:</hi> But being ask'd if He did believe it was her Hand, He reply's, <hi>No:</hi> And why? <hi>Because it does not suit her Character.</hi> Now let the World judge, if this contains any more than if the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had said, because She was my Daughter, or the Brother, because She was my Sister, we won't believe it,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150226:18"/> least the World should look on Her to have been a Lewd Woman.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Because there was no mention made of these Letters, till the common Report of Her being with Child (which had been industriously spread Abroad by several, but by none more zealously than by a Nominal Quaker, her former Admirer) was proved to be false,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If these Letters were taken Notice of, so soon as the Report of her being with Child, it was very early, for that Morning She was taken out of the Water, it was whisper'd in the Country, and at Night I heard from some in <hi>London,</hi> that they believ'd it very likely for Her to be with Child: And that to prevent the ensuing Infamy, She had made her self away. This was no more than what is generally Suspected, when a Single Gentlewoman is by any means Accessory to Her own Death. So that without dispute, if the Nominal Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker had not been concern'd in it, the Report would have spread without him. But I judge this <hi>Epithet</hi> is bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on Him, not so much for that He thought and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported Her to be with Child, which Hundreds did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides Him at that time, but because He was so very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious to prove her Hand by his Receipt.</p>
            <p>This may indeed be thought a mean Spirited Action from Him, as He had been Her former Admirer: And I think if her Hand writing could have been proved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Appearance, He should have stirred last. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I would not have You so very angry at Him, since I don't find that He got any thing more by it, than to have the Judge inform'd, that He was one of their own Sect. And if for this only, He must be a <hi>Nominal Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> I could tell You of some that have had great Parts to Act in this Prosecution, that are as far from being Real <hi>Quakers</hi> (if to be so is a Perfection) as Mr. <hi>B.</hi>—</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:150226:18"/>
            <p>Page 22. 4. <hi>Because Mr.</hi> Mason <hi>and Mr.</hi> Archer, <hi>on the Tryal Swear that Mr.</hi> Cowper <hi>Deposed that Mrs.</hi> Stout <hi>was a Modest Person,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>When Mr. <hi>Cowper</hi> was before the Coroner, He dreamt not of the approaching Storm that was coming upon Him: And I think 'twas not reasonable that he should concern himself at all with her Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter; there were not wanting those, who were ready enough to think He had been too familiar with Her, and that on some resent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment taken at his Carriage to Her, she had destroy'd her self: So that if 'twere only to wipe off this Suspicion, His Account of Her was no other than what any Man under his Circumstances, might have given. I can't tell what you might have thought of Him, but had he told the Coroner he knew She was Melancholy, that it was upon his Account, for that having formerly been very civil to Her, he grew of late sick of her Acquaintance, and that because in his last Visit, he had betray'd some little Inifference, and notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Importunity, would not stay to lye at her House, She had therefore in a Passion, thrown her Self into the River; if Mr. <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> I say, had given the Coroner such a Relation as this, I should have thought him a Person of very little understanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 23. As to her Melancholy, I believe it was such as did make her Head and her Heart ake also; and that it was more than a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Hemicrane, whatever you (who had perhaps no great intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with Her) may imagine, or her Mother and Brother give out I am satisfi'd there wants no Proof of such a Melancholy, as was next to a Distraction. There is a certain Gentlewoman, now in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who cannot deny that She had heard Mrs. <hi>Stout</hi> wish her self Dead, saying She was the miserable'st Creature living, and that She hoped if 'twere possible, to die after such a Manner, that the World might know nothing of the Matter, nor ever so much as mention there had been such a Person living. But indeed her Melancholy is too well attested to be so much as doubted of, by any disinterested Person, and therefore as you are apt to think, there are many Friends and Relations, bigotted to a Party, that will not Boggle to tell a Lie, to save a Friend or neer Relation from— I suppose you mean the <hi>Gallows;</hi> so on the other hand I believe there may be those in the World, who would not scruple to tell an untruth, which is of neer kin to a Lye, and if 'twere in their Power, would bring a Man to the said Place, rather than it should be thought a neer Friend and Relation, was in Love with a married Man.</p>
            <p>The Gentlewoman you take Notice of, so much importuned by the Deceased to stay with her that Night, if she has not altered her Story, will acknowledge that Mrs. <hi>Stout</hi> did tell her she was very much Indisposed, and farther saith she, you see I am very Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150226:19"/> so that it will be the greater Unkindness, if You leave me at this time alone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 25. You say there are a thousand Pounds wanting of her Original Fortune, I wish you had told us whether you set a side the Charge of the Prosecution, if you include this in the want, one half might be expended that way; for I suppose there was nothing spared to carry it on.</p>
            <p>I have heard of Peoples wanting that which they never had; and I am credibly inform'd this is the Case in debate. Some of your Country Men, that have been many Years acquainted in the Family, do tell me there is as much found as ever She could be thought Worth, but if You would be credited, You must give bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Proof than Yours, or Her Relations say so. However I think this to be very little Material, She might, though in some things very Frugal, in others be as Extravagant, but which way soever 'tis gone it seems nothing less can repay it, but the Lives of Persons who had never seen Her.</p>
            <p>Though the <hi>Quakers</hi> Affirmation will not be taken in Criminal Cases ('twas well I think that it was not admitted in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar One), yet they have now the Priviledge to Publish their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, why they Suspected Mr. <hi>Cowper</hi> to be privy to the Receipt of any of her Money, more than that which the Writings found in her Custody, and his own Acknowledgment do Evince. I am sure he has bid them a fair Defiance, having openly challeng'd the Worst of his Adversaries, to discover what they can of this Nature.</p>
            <p>If they think fit to draw up any thing of this kind, I should advise them to make use of some abler Clerk, than the Author of the <hi>Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Letter: For, if he has the Management, 'tis a great chance if we are not entertained with one of Mrs. <hi>Gurrey</hi>'s Dreams, or some such ridiculous <hi>Innuendo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 26. In this Place, we are once more acquainted with the use of the Epiglottis, which you will have continually to close on the Mouth of the <hi>Aspera Arteria</hi> unless in Expiration. On the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, I have told you (and will submit my self to any <hi>Anatomist</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi>) that it is for the most part open, and never exactly closes but upon <hi>Deglutition,</hi> so that whatever you build upon that Notion, must fall to the ground.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 27. I think 'tis but reasonable, that Mr. Baron <hi>Hatsell</hi> return his Thanks to you, for the Compliment you put upon him in the close of your Letter. I am ready to apprehend that there is no Tryal suffered to be Printed, till after the Examination of the Judge, and his Permission first obtain'd; and therefore must needs think Omssi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Alterations, especially of great Moment, as these should be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150226:19"/> which you insinuate; is a very great Injustice to the World, an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to Truth, and too sinister an Action for a Judge to be guilty of. But let who will stand in your way, I see you will have a Fling at them, and rather than be thought to have nothing at all to say, will be telling us of that which (if possible) comes to less.</p>
            <p>Thus to heighten a Suspicion of Guilt, we are entertain'd with a Tale of a Tub, about Mr. <hi>Stevens</hi>'s being ill, or as you express it, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with a strange sort of Fit. I hope, Sir, 'tis not always an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Man's Guilt, that he cannot carry himself unconcernedly, when he sees his Life hanging by a Hair, or depending on the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of a Word or two from the Fore-man of a Jury: 'Tis time enough to Censure, when we our selves have undergone the Tryal.</p>
            <p>Your Story of the Wine-Cooper I have never heard of, and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly I am so desperate Jealous of your Relations, that I dare not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them till they come with more Authority: When I have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd my self, I shall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etter able to give you my Opinion.</p>
            <p>Your Prayer, methinks, with which you conclude, had better have been left out; since, though it wants the Length of the <hi>Pharisees,</hi> whoever takes notice of the Spirit that runs through the whole Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, will need no Arguments to persuade him that it proceeds from an Hypocrite. There is little Appearance that 'tis your Desire the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent may be cleared from Aspersions cast undeservedly on them, when for more than Twenty Pages, you are venting the utmost of your Malice, and by the basest means imaginable, would insinuate those Gentlemen are Guilty, who for any thing you know of the Matter, may be as innocent as your self.</p>
            <p>Let me tell you, Sir, I think it a very bold Attempt, and such as 'tis great Pity does not come under the Lash of the Law. When a Gentleman has taken his Tryal, and it does appear upon that Tryal, there is no Proof of the Fact he is charged with, nor indeed any thing on, which to ground so much as a Suspicion, unless that of his being unfortunately the last Person in her Company: In a Word, when Faction and Personal Prejudice, appear the only Motives of the Prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, whoever brings the Business a fresh on the Stage, does only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the Restlesness of his own Mind, and plainly evidence that he is neither a true Gentleman, nor a good Christian.</p>
            <p>I have lookt over your Postscript, and as in many Places of the Letter, perceive through the Weakness of your Intellect, or your Unfitness for the Controversy, you have made good your Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick of betraying a little Ignorance.</p>
            <p>First of all you tell your Friend. You make no doubt but he has heard, that the Surgeons that open'd Mrs. <hi>Stout's</hi> Body, deposed she was a Virgin. Now if he had heard as much before, as you make
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150226:20"/> no doubt he had, I don't see to what purpose, or what News it could be to inform him of that he had heard before; but being fearful it had not reach'd every Body's Ear, I make no doubt this Intelligence is to inform the World. But doubt you as you please, had I found the Surgeons deposed as you report, I should be ready to doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were Wise Men or Fools.</p>
            <p>I find nothing like it in the Affidavit, of which you say you have delivered us a true Copy.</p>
            <p>They tell us indeed, <hi>They found the</hi> Uterus <hi>perfectly free and empty, and of the natural Figure and Magnitude usually in Virgins.</hi> But surely this will not amount to a Deposition, that she was a Virgin; all that can be hence inferr'd, is only that she had not conceived, and if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> possible for a Woman in Coitu, to miss of Conception, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> missing of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onception, the Womb may, notwithstanding the Carnal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>in the natural Form and Figure usually in Virgins, why then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is implies no more than a bare Probability that she had not known a Man.</p>
            <p>I must confess till now, I never heard that the Figure or Magnitude of the Womb, were numbred amongst the indubitable Marks of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity; and as to the State of the <hi>Vagina,</hi> the <hi>Myr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>form Caruncles,</hi> and <hi>Hymen,</hi> which Mother <hi>Peppercorn</hi> her self could only guess at: There is no notice at all taken, if there had indeed, it would only have furnisht Matter of Derision: The Body having been so long inter'd▪ So that you see, for any thing pretended to in the Affidavit, or else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, she might not be a Virgin, though Charity should oblige us to hope at least, that she was.</p>
            <closer/>
            <postscript>
               <head>POSTCRIPT.</head>
               <p>SInce this REPLY went into the Press, I have been inform'd by a Gentleman of unquestionable Credit, that the Story of the Wine-Cooper at the Close of the <hi>Hertford-Letter,</hi> took its Rise only from what follows.</p>
               <p>There was, it seems, a Person going down to the Assizes, who had the Misfortune to be thrown from his Horse, and was taken up as dead; being carried to his Lodging, he began to rave and to talk idly; which was no more than the Effect of a Delirium, arising from the Concussion of his Brain; which might have made any Man Light headed as well as he, and which nothing but one as mad could have improv'd after such a Manner as the Letter writer has done.</p>
               <p>By this, the Publick may be inform'd of the Disingenuity, not to say down right Villany, of some People in the World; who missing their Design of taking away a Man's Life, seek all possible ways of Murdering his Reputation.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150226:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>